<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A particular charge or impeachment in the name of his Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax and the army under his command, against Denzill Holles Esquire, Sir Philip Stapleton, Sir William Lewis ... [et al.] members of the honorable House of Commons. / by the appointment of his Excel. Sir Thomas Fairfax, and the Councell of Warre. Signed John Rushworth Seere.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Army. Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09004</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E741DA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R174975</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">62369185</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 62369185</idno>
            <idno type="VID">187881</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09004)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 187881)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2847:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A particular charge or impeachment in the name of his Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax and the army under his command, against Denzill Holles Esquire, Sir Philip Stapleton, Sir William Lewis ... [et al.] members of the honorable House of Commons. / by the appointment of his Excel. Sir Thomas Fairfax, and the Councell of Warre. Signed John Rushworth Seere.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Army. Council.</author>
                  <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
                  <author>Rushworth, John, 1612?-1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for George Whittington, at the Blew Anchor in Cornhill neere the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title within double line border; initial letter.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages cropped and misnumbered.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Holles, Denzil Holles, --  Baron, 1599-1680.</term>
               <term>Stapleton, Philip, --  Sir.</term>
               <term>Lewis, William, --  Sir.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  House of Commons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Impeachments --  England --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:187881:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187881:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187881:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187881:2"/>
            <p>A particular CHARGE OR IMPEACHMENT, in the name of His Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, AND The Army under his Command.</p>
            <p>AGAINST
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Denzill Hollis</hi>Eſq;</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>William Lewis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>John Clotworthy.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>William VValler.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>John Maynard,</hi> Knights.</item>
                  <item>Major Gen. <hi>Maſſey.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Glynn</hi>Eſq; Recorder of <hi>London.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>VValter Long</hi>Eſq;</item>
                  <item>Col. <hi>Edward Harley.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>And <hi>Anthony Nicoll</hi>Eſq;</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Members of the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BY the appointment of His Excellency Sir</hi> Thomas Fairfax, <hi>and his Councell of VVarre.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Signed, JOHN RUSHVVORTH. Secr.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Imprinted at <hi>London,</hi> for <hi>George Whittington</hi> at the <hi>Blew Anchor</hi> in <hi>Cornehill</hi> neere the <hi>Royall Exchange.</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:187881:3"/>
            <head>July 8. 1647.</head>
            <p>THe Charge was preſented to the Houſe of Commons Tueſday the 6. of June by Col. <hi>Scroope,</hi> Col. <hi>Okey,</hi> Col. <hi>Hewſon,</hi> Col. <hi>Pride,</hi> Lieutenant Col. <hi>Bowen,</hi> Lieutenant Col. <hi>Goffe,</hi> Major <hi>Rainsborow,</hi> Capt <hi>Berry,</hi> Capt. <hi>Clerke,</hi> Captaine <hi>Carter,</hi> Capt. <hi>Rolph,</hi> Mr. <hi>Saxby,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gethings,</hi> who atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at the Parliament Door, were ſent for in, and ſtanding at the Barre Col. <hi>Scroope</hi> ſpake to this effect: That they were appointed by the Generall and the Army under his command to preſent to this Honourable Houſe a particular Charge or Impeachment againſt ſeverall Members thereof, viz. Mr. <hi>Hollis,</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> Sir <hi>William Lewis.</hi> Sir <hi>John Clot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy,</hi> Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> Sir <hi>John Maynard,</hi> Knights, Major Generall <hi>Maſſey, John Glynn</hi> Recorder of London, <hi>Walter Long</hi> Eſquire, Col. <hi>Edward Harley,</hi> and <hi>Anthony Nicoll</hi> Eſquire; and that in the name of his Excellency and the Army they did here impeach the ſaid Members of high Crimes and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanours; humbly tendering the ſame to this Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Houſe.</p>
            <p>Which being done, the Speaker ſent for the Charge by the Clerke of the Houſe; the Officers being deſired to withdraw, the Members impeached were ſent for, and the Charge read in the Houſe, but the debate thereupon was deferred till Thurſday, at which time the Officers attended and ſent in, and acquainted Mr. Speaker that they were at the doore for an anſwer, that ſo they might give an account to the Army; But other weighty matters taking up the day, the Houſe ſent to informe the Officers that they reſolved the debate upon the Charge on Fryday July 9. at whiah time they are againe to attend the Houſe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:187881:3"/>
            <head>A particular <hi>Charge</hi> or <hi>Impeachment,</hi> in the name o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> His Excellency Sir THOMAS FAIRFAX, and the Army under his Command: Againſt <hi>Denzill Holles,</hi> Eſq; Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> Sir <hi>Will. Lewis,</hi> Sir <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> Sir <hi>Will. Waller,</hi> Sir <hi>John Maynard,</hi> Knights Maj. Gen. <hi>Maſſey, John Glyn</hi>Eſq; Recorder of <hi>London, Walter Long</hi> Eſq; Col. <hi>Edw. Harley,</hi> and <hi>Anthony Nicholl,</hi> Eſq; Members of the Houſe of Commons.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas on the 15. day of <hi>June</hi> laſt, the heads of a Charge were delivered in the name of the ſaid Army, unto the Courts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to be ſent up to the Parliament againſt the perſons above named. Now in proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and maintenance thereof, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the power thereby reſerved, it is in the name of the ſaid Army more particularly charged againſt the ſaid perſons as followeth:</p>
            <p n="1">I. That the ſaid Maſter <hi>Denzill Holles,</hi> during the late Warre, in proſecution of the evill deſignes expreſſed in the generall Heads or Articles formerly exhibited, contrary to the truſt repoſed in him, contrary to his Oath taken in June, 1643. and contrary to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Parliament dated in <hi>October,</hi> 1643. hath aſsiſted the King in the late unnaturall Warre, and held correſpondence and intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence with the Enemy againſt the Parliament, in manner following. <hi>viz,</hi> He the ſaid Maſter <hi>Holles,</hi> being one of the ſpeciall Commiſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for the Parliament, to preſent Propoſitions of both Houſes to the King at Oxford; did privately, and contrary to his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, at ſeverall times, make his addreſſes unto the Kings Party, there then in Armes againſt the Parliament namely, unto the Earle of <hi>Lindſey,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Southampton,</hi> the Lord <hi>Savill,</hi> and others; and did ſecretly plot and adviſe them againſt the Parliament; and did intimate unto them, or one of them, That the ſaid Propoſitions then ſent unto His Majeſty by the Parliament were unreaſonable: And the ſaid Maſter <hi>Holles</hi> being demanded what anſwer he would adviſe the King to make to the ſaid Propoſitions; he the ſaid Maſter <hi>Holles</hi> did adviſe that the King ſhould demand a Treaty however, and then declare how unreaſonable the Propoſitions were and that yet, for the peace of the Kingdome, His Majeſty would treat upon them; but withall wiſhed the ſaid Treaty might be in London, whither the King himſelf ſhould come upon ſecurity. And he the ſaid Maſter <hi>Holles,</hi> adding that there was nothing in the world that the violent party (meaning the well-affected party to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the Enemy, did ſo much feare as his Majeſties com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to London, which would be a certaine diſſolution of their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:187881:4"/>
and Power: And the ſaid Maſter <hi>Holles</hi> bad thoſe ſaid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or one of them, aſſure the King that if His Majeſty knew as much as he (the ſaid Maſter <hi>Holles</hi>) knew, His Majeſty would take his Horſe and be at London the next day, or words to that effect. And it being againe demanded whether (if the King ſhould be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to come) it would be accepted of? he the ſaid Mr. <hi>Holles</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to anſwered, that certainly it would be much oppoſed, but yet he the ſaid Mr <hi>Holles</hi> was confident, that he and his Party (meaning ſome of the Members above-named, and others) ſhould carry it, and wiſhed the King to put it upon that tryall. And the ſaid Mr. <hi>Holles</hi> was deſired by the ſaid Earle of <hi>Lindſey,</hi> Earle of <hi>Southhampton</hi> and Lord <hi>Savill,</hi> or one of them, that he would be pleaſed to draw ſuch an anſwer in writing to the ſaid Propoſitions, as he deſired the King ſhould ſend; and the ſaid Earle of <hi>Southampton,</hi> who was that night to lye in the Kings Bed-Chamber, would perſwade the King to condiſcend unto it; and thereupon the ſaid Maſter <hi>Hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew, and either the ſame day, or the next day following the ſaid Maſter <hi>Holles</hi> accordingly carried in his hand unto the ſaid Lords, or one of them, a paper ready written, which (as he ſaid) was ſuch an anſwer to the ſaid Propoſitions, as he had drawne for the King to ſend to the Parliament; which was taken by the ſaid Lords, or one of them, and carryed to the King to be conſidered of; and ſo much thereof as adviſed the Kings comming to London was laid by, the King fearing to adventure himſelfe, but the reſt of the ſaid Paper the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> (who writ the Kings Anſwer to the Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) made uſe of, in the ſame words as the ſaid Maſter <hi>Holles</hi> had ſet downe And the ſaid Maſter <hi>Holles</hi> to ingratiate himſelfe with the Kings Party, did about the ſame time revile the well-affected Members of the Houſe of Commons, declaring unto the ſaid Kings Party at Oxford, or ſome of them, that thoſe well-affected Members (which, to render them the more odious as he concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, he named the violent Independant party) had ill intentions and great averſeneſſe to peace; and that nothing would be more pleaſing to them then for the King to refuſe the Propoſitions how unreaſonable ſoever the ſame were; And he alſo then ſaid, That the Commiſsioners of Scotland were very weary of that violent party, and that they being deſperate to eſtabliſh their Presbytery here as in Scotland, made their addreſſes to him, the ſaid Maſter <hi>Holles</hi> and his Party All which tended to the protracting of the ſaid late Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re and to the hinderance of an happy peace</p>
            <p>And the ſaid Mr. <hi>Holles</hi> did alſo after that receive from the ſaid E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rle of <hi>Lindſey</hi> at Oxford a Letter written in white Inke, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſome ſecret deſigne, and kept it from the knowledge of the Houſe from February till about July after, when it was diſcovered by him that brought it, but the Letter it ſelfe was by the ſaid Mr. <hi>Holles</hi> (after he had read it) burnt; and the ſaid Earle of <hi>Lindſey</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:187881:4"/>
moved the King for a Paſſe for the ſaid Mr. <hi>Holles</hi> to goe to Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, but the King refuſed to grant it, ſaying, <hi>That</hi> Holles <hi>did him better ſervice in the Parliament then he could doe him at Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. That the ſaid Mr. <hi>Holles,</hi> and Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> during the ſaid late Warres, when the Earle of <hi>Lindſey</hi> went from the Tower of London to Oxford, ſent ſeverall Meſſages of intelligence to the Earl of <hi>Dorſet,</hi> and Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> thereby aſſuring them, that they, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Holles,</hi> and Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton</hi> did better ſervice for the King here in Parliament then they could doe him if they were at Oxford; and the ſaid Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton</hi> deſired, that the ſaid Earle of <hi>Dorſet</hi> would preſerve him the ſaid Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> and his friends in the good opinion of the Party at Oxford (which was then the Kings Garriſon) and he, the ſaid Sir <hi>Philip</hi> would doe as much for his Lordſhip, and his friends here with the Parliament. And the ſaid Mr. <hi>Holles,</hi> and Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> the more to ingratiate themſelves into the favour of the Enemy, did of their owne accord without any direction of the Parliament, draw up other Propoſitions then thoſe mentioned in the preceding Articles, which they affirmed were in their judgements fit for the King to grant, and for the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to deſire; and being ſo drawn up, ſent them privately to his Majeſty, without any Authority of Parliament to warrant the ſame.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That the ſaid Mr. <hi>Holles,</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> Sir <hi>William Lewis,</hi> Sir <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> Sir <hi>John Maynard,</hi> Major Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Maſſie,</hi> Mr. <hi>Glyn,</hi> Mr. <hi>Long,</hi> Col. <hi>Edward Harley,</hi> and <hi>Anthony Nicholl,</hi> in the moneths of March, Aprill, May and June laſt paſt, and at other times in proſecution of the evill deſignes in the ſeverall generall Heads mentioned, have frequently aſſembled, and met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether at the Lady <hi>Carliles</hi> Lodgings in White Hall, and in other places, with divers other Perſons diſ-affected to the State (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Authority of Parliament) for holding correſpondency with the Queene of <hi>England</hi> now in <hi>France,</hi> and her participants, with an intent by ſuch ſecret and clandeſtine treaties amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to put conditions upon the Parliament, and to bring in the King upon their owne termes and having a great power upon the Treaſure of this Kingdome, have therewith maintained, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by Penſions and otherwiſe the Queens Party in <hi>Fran e,</hi> thereby to beget a ſecond and more bloody War in this Kingdome; and they<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or ſome, or one of them aſſured the Queene 40000. <hi>l. per annum,</hi> if ſhe would asſiſt them in their Deſigne, and that they would do more for the King then the Army would do, and that they would finde out ſome meanes to deſtroy the Army and their friends.</p>
            <p n="4">IIII. That in further purſuance of the ſame evill Deſignes they, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Holles,</hi> Sir <hi>Phillip Stapleton,</hi> Sir <hi>William Lewis</hi> Sir <hi>John Clot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy,</hi> Sir <hi>William VValler,</hi> and Major Generall <hi>Maſſie</hi> by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination aforeſaid within the ſpace of three moneths laſt paſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Authority of Parliament invited the <hi>Scots,</hi> and other For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:187881:5"/>
Forces to come into this Kingdome in a Hoſtile manner, to abet and asſiſt them in the perſecuting and effecting of their ſaid deſignes. And the ſaid Mr. <hi>Holles</hi> very lately ſent to the ſaid Queene of <hi>England,</hi> then and ſtill in <hi>France,</hi> adviſing her amongſt other things ſpeedily to ſend the Prince into <hi>Scotland,</hi> to march into this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the head of an Army, and did ſend a ſpeciall Meſſenger to her for ſuch ends and purpoſes. And the ſaid Mr. <hi>Holles,</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> Sir <hi>VVilliam Lewis,</hi> Sir <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> Sir <hi>John Maynard,</hi> Mr. <hi>Glyn,</hi> Major Generall <hi>Maſſie,</hi> Mr. <hi>Long,</hi> Col. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Harley,</hi> and <hi>Anthony Nicholl,</hi> have under hand of their owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, without Authority of Parliament liſted, or cauſed, or procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be liſted divers Commanders and Souldiers, endeavouring thereby to leavy and raiſe a new Warre in this Kingdome, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect themſelves in their unjuſt Oppresſions, and factious Deſignes, and have at ſeverall times within the ſpace of two moneths laſt paſt invited, encouraged, abetted, and counſelled multitudes of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mado Officers and Souldiers, and other rude perſons, tumultuouſly and violently to gather together at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to affright and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault the Members of Parliament in their paſſage to and from the Houſe, to offer violence to the Houſe it ſelfe, by locking the doore thereof upon them, and ſo impriſoning them; and by ſuch violences, outrages, and threats, to awe and enforce the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="5">V. That the ſaid Maſter <hi>Holles,</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> and Mr <hi>Glyn,</hi> have be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n and are obſtructers and prejudgers of ſeverall Petitions to the Parliament, for redreſſe of publique grievances; and the ſaid Maſter <hi>Holles,</hi> and Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> in the moneth of <hi>May</hi> laſt paſt, did abuſe and affront divers Petitioners; who in a peaceable manner then attended the Committee, whereof Colonell <hi>Lee</hi> was Chaireman; not onely reviling and reproaching them, but vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently haleing, and boyſterouſly aſſaulting them, and offered to draw their ſwords upon Major <hi>Tuleday,</hi> and others of the ſaid Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners; and without any authority or power committed <hi>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Tew,</hi> one of the Petitioners; and ſoone afterwards, by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement of the ſaid Maſter <hi>Holles</hi> and Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> and upon their miſ-information to the Houſe, the ſaid Major <hi>Tuleday,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Tewe,</hi> were impriſoned, not being permitted to ſpeake for themſelves; and the ſaid Maſter <hi>Glyn</hi> about three moneths ſince, cauſed the ſaid <hi>Nicholas Tewe</hi> to be impriſoned in <hi>Newgate,</hi> and to be deteyned a long time there, for no other cauſe, but for having a Petition about him which was to be preſented to the Houſe.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. That the ſaid Sir <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> Sir <hi>VVilliam VValler,</hi> and Ma or Generall <hi>Maſſey,</hi> have lately in proſecution of the ſaid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes in the ſaid generall heads mentioned, againſt the knowne Lawes of this Realme, and Rules and Articles of Warre made by Parliament, by an Arbitrary power impriſoned ſome Members of the Army without any authority, particularly Enſigne <hi>Nichols,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:187881:5"/>
whoſe Pockets they without authority cauſed to be ſearched, and ſeverall papers to be taken from him, contrary to the liberty of every Subject, and cauſed him to be ſent a Priſoner from the head Quarters to <hi>London,</hi> without the authority or privity of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, or the chiefe Officers of the Army commanding in his abſence.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. That in or about the moneth of <hi>March</hi> laſt, (there being a Petition intended from the Officers and Souldiers of the Army to their Generall (for ſuch things onely as were juſtly due unto them, and concerning them meerely as Souldiers) The ſaid Sir <hi>VVilliam VValler,</hi> Sir <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Edward Harley,</hi> a Member of the Army, (having gotten into their hands a Copy of the ſaid Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition) by combination with the other Members above mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with an intent to abuſe the Parliament into prejudices and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies againſt the proceedings of the Army, concerning the ſaid Petition (they well knowing that the ſaid Army ſtood in their way, and hindereth them from bringing to paſſe the deſignes in the ſaid generall Charge expreſſed) did falſly and malitiouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the Houſe, That the ſaid Petition was contrived and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted to debauch and diſ-oblige the Army from the Parliament; And that it was managed and carried on by divers principall Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in the Army; That Orders were given out for the reading of it in the head of every Regiment, and whoſoever would not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe it, ſhould be put out of the Muſters, and caſhiered the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: And by thoſe and other aggravations, did repreſent it to the Houſe as a deſigne againſt the Parliament: Further adding, That ſome Regiments which were remote, were ſent for, to joyne with the reſt of the Army for that purpoſe; by which miſ-informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they the ſaid Members did the ſame day procure a peremptory Order to the Generall, to ſuppreſſe the ſaid Petition.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. That ſome few daies after, Colonell <hi>Edward Harley,</hi> by the combination aforeſaid, and in purſuance of the ſame deſignes, did produce to the Houſe a Letter, ſuppoſed to be written from within the Quarters of the Army, to him the ſaid Colonell <hi>Harley,</hi> by a perſon not named, whereby it was informed that Colonell <hi>Harleys</hi> Lieutenant Colonell had drawne his Regiment to a rendez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouze, and had cauſed the ſaid Petition to be read at the head of it, and that he threatned to caſhiere and put out of the Muſters all that would not ſubſcribe it; And that the deſigne of the Army therein, was to inſlave the Parliament and Kingdom (if the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment proceeded not to ſome high reſolution) or to that effect, as by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaid Letter (relation thereunto being had) may appeare; And although the ſubſtance of the ſaid Letter was moſt untrue, and no author thereof appeared, nor could be produced, although a Committee was appointed for examination thereof, and it was much preſſed the author ſhould be diſcovered; yet the ſaid Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Harley,</hi> Sir <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> and Sir <hi>VVilliam VValler,</hi> did ſo avow
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:187881:6"/>
the reality of the ſaid Letter, and that the contents thereof would be made good: As that thereby, and by other falſe ſuggeſtions of theirs againſt the Army, they procured the Houſe (upon a long debate which held till about 8. of the clock at night) to Order, That a Committee of five Members (whereof the ſaid Maſter <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> was one) ſhould prepare a Declaration to be brought in to the Houſe the next morning, ſignifying the Houſes diſlike of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the Army upon that Petition, as by the ſaid Order dated <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> laſt, may appeare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which ſetling of the ſaid buſineſſe, for that night moſt of the Members departed, as conceiving nothing would be done thereupon till the next day, and that then they might have a free debate concerning the ſame; But the Houſe ſtill continuing to ſit (upon the diſpach of ſome Letters formerly ordered) the ſaid Maſter</hi> Holles <hi>by the ſame combination, and in further proſecution of the ſaid evill deſignes, having of himſelf (without the Committee) prepared a Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration againſt the Petition it ſelfe, contrary to the intention and direction of the ſaid Order, and contrary to the rules of Juſtice, and uſuall courſe of Parliament, did the ſame night about ten of the clock, on purpoſe to ſurpriſe the Houſe, preſent the ſame Declaration to the Houſe, whereby the ſaid Petitioners were (without being heard) declared Enemies to the State, and obſtructers of the reliefe of</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>if they perſiſted therein, (as by the ſame Declaration, relation being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto had, may appeare) and did procure it to be then paſſed accordingly, to the great diſhonour of the Parliament and their proceedings, to the inſufferable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, the juſt provocations, diſcouragement, and diſcontent of the Army, to the trouble and danger of the whole Kingdome, to the hindering of the reliefe of</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and other the evill conſequences in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaid generall Charges expreſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">IX. That by the ſame and the like falſe informations and ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions the ſaid Colonell <hi>Harley</hi> (then a Member of the Army) Sir <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> Sir <hi>William VValler,</hi> and the ſaid other perſons did ſhortly after the ſaid Declaration ſo made as afore-ſaid, procure divers eminent and faithfull Officers of the Army, namely, Liev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Generall <hi>Hamond,</hi> Colonell <hi>Hamond,</hi> Colonell <hi>Lilburne,</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenant Colonell <hi>Pride</hi> and others, to be all ſent for from their char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in the Army to appeare at the Barre of the Houſe to make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer in relation to the ſaid Petition, againſt whom when they came thither they could charge or prove nothing at all in ſo much as the Houſe thought fit immediatly to diſcharge them. And whereas there was a Committee appointed to examine and conſider of the truth or falſhood of them and the ſaid members informing were appointed to produce their proofs and evidence to the ſame before the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, though they have ſince then been often urged, called upon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and demanded to produce their proofes and evidenes thereto (if they had any) and have been plainely told, that if they did not proceed ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to doe it, they ſhould be accounted the Authours and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſers of the ſaid falſhoods, and reparation would accordingly be demanded againſt them: <hi>Yet they have not to this day produced any</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:187881:6"/>
proofes or evidence to any of the ſaid informations or ſuggeſtions, whereby the Parliament and the Army were ſo much abuſed as before is declared: nor could they, or any of them be hitherto perſwaded to give in to the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee any charge againſt the ſaid Officers of the Army, which they have then or ſince procured to be ſent for as aforeſaid, but have held divers of them in a long and chargeable attendance upon the Houſe, without any thing laid to their charge, untill the Houſe was pleaſed to diſcharge them.</p>
            <p n="10">X. That the ſaid Maſter <hi>Hollis,</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> Sir <hi>VVilliam Lewis,</hi> Sir <hi>William VValler,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Clotworthy</hi> &amp; Major Generall <hi>Maſſie,</hi> in further purſuance of the deſignes mentioned in the generall heads charged againſt them, have been great inſtruments in the obſtructing of the reliefe of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and within the ſpace of two moneths laſt paſt, did falſly informe the Houſe, that by their procurement there were fifty Companies of Foot, and ten Troopes of Horſe of this Army ingaged for <hi>Ireland,</hi> upon the termes, and under the conduct then by the Parliament propounded; and the more to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude the Parliament herein, they, or ſome of them by the combination afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, did procure divers Officers then in this Army, namely, Collonel <hi>Butler,</hi> Lievtenant Collonel <hi>Iackſon,</hi> Major <hi>Gooday,</hi> and others, to give in their names, as liſting themſelves for <hi>Ireland</hi> (on the ſaid termes, and conduct propounded) when as thoſe Officers did at the ſame time declare themſelves unwilling thereunto, and reſolved not to goe ſerve in <hi>Ireland</hi> on any termes whatſoever; they the ſaid Members under-hand aſſuring them, that though they made uſe of their names, yet they ſhould not goe for that ſervice: They have likewiſe untruly informed the Houſe and given in the names of many, conſiderable Officers of the Army namely, Captain <hi>Pennifather,</hi> and Captain <hi>Burges,</hi> of Collonel <hi>Butlers</hi> Regiment; Captain <hi>Clarke,</hi> and foure or more commiſſion Officers of Sir <hi>Hardreſſe VVallers</hi> Regiment, and others, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been ſubſcribed for <hi>Ireland</hi> who did not ſo ingage or ſubſcribe, nor give any conſent thereto, but did then, and have ever ſince utterly diſavowed and denied the ſame.</p>
            <p>And about the ſame time they alſo reported to the Houſe the name and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of Lievtenant Collonel <hi>Farington,</hi> as being then a Lievtenant Coll. of this Army and ingaging for himſelfe and his Regiment for <hi>Ireland</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the ſaid <hi>Farrington</hi> had beene caſhiered the Army a yeare and an halfe before. By which and other their untrue informations and reports of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The Parliament was abuſed and miſled into a conceipt and confidence of a ſtrength out of the Army, then ſuppoſed to be ingaged and ready for <hi>Jreland</hi> on their owne termes when as in truth the ſame was but a meere deluſion, and which was ſo contrived on purpoſe to occaſion a ſlighting and neglecting of the Army, as ſuppoſing no further uſe for them.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. Whereas part of three Regiments of foote (<hi>viz.</hi> Collonel <hi>Herberts,</hi> Collonel <hi>Kemps</hi> and Collonel <hi>Grayes</hi>) were by order of the Houſe advanced towards the reliefe of <hi>Ireland</hi> as farre as <hi>Bromeſgrave</hi> in the County of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:187881:7"/>
               <hi>Worceſter.</hi> The ſaid Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> Maſter <hi>Hollis,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Clotworthy,</hi> Sir <hi>William Lewis,</hi> Major Generall <hi>Maſſie,</hi> Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Glyn,</hi> by combination aforeſaid, did of their owne accord without the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or direction of the Houſe, on the ſixt day of <hi>Iune</hi> laſt, (being Sabbath day and without ſummoning a Committee) command thoſe forces backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine as farre as <hi>Reading,</hi> with an evill intent to draw forces together to beget a new Warre in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">XII. That the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Clotworthy,</hi> in proſecution of the deſignes in the ſaid generall charge expreſſed, hath in the yeares. 1642. 1643. 1644. and ſince, converted ſeverall great ſummes of money (which by ſeverall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Parliament and of the Iriſh Committee were deſigned for the reliefe of <hi>Ireland</hi>) to his owne particular uſe; namely the ſumme of two hundred and eighty pounds, which by Order of both Houſes dated the eleventh of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary</hi> 1642. was to be payd for twenty butts of ſack for <hi>Jreland,</hi> ſeven hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pound which the ſame day was alſo ordered for two thouſand ſwords, three hundred pounds which by order of the ſaid Iriſh Committee dated the fift of <hi>Aprill</hi> 1643. was deſigned for one hundred and twenty paire of piſtolls, and divers other ſummes of money upon ſeverall other orders which he the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Clotworthy</hi> from time to time received for the uſe and reliefe of <hi>Ireland,</hi> but were not imployed to the uſes, by the ſaid orders intended and directed, but to his the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Clotworthyes</hi> owne private uſe as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, And that he hath within two yeares laſt paſt received ſeverall fummes of monyes, armes, and other proviſions for a troope of horſe, which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended he had raiſed in <hi>Ireland,</hi> whereas he had not, nor did raiſe or furniſh any ſuch troope as he pretended, And that he the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Clotworthy</hi> for money and other rewards hath preferred <hi>John Davis,</hi> and <hi>William Summers</hi> and others to be entruſted with the Iriſh affaires who have kept correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency with the enemy, and have defrauded the State of other great ſummes of money, and he hath beene privy to and a ſharer in ſuch their actions.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. That about <hi>November</hi> laſt paſt the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Clotworthy</hi> being by the Parliament ſent a Commiſſioner with others into <hi>Ireland,</hi> who all had a joynt power or authority to treate with the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> for the ſpace of foure dayes and no more, he the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Clotworthy</hi> contrary to the ſpeciall truſt repoſed in him, held ſecret intelligence with the ſaid Earl of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> by cypher or character without the conſent or knowledge of thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in Commiſſion with him, and many weekes after the time ſo limited was expired, &amp; about the ſame time he the ſaid Sir <hi>Joh. Colworthy</hi> held the like ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret intelligence with the L. <hi>George Digby</hi> then in <hi>Ireland</hi> beyond the time prefix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and without the conſent of the ſaid other Commiſſioners, and in order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the Lord <hi>Ormond</hi> and <hi>Digby,</hi> lately employed one <hi>Slingsby</hi> who pretends a deſigne about the Prince to come into this Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="14">XIIII. That the ſaid Sir <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> Maſter <hi>Hollis,</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton</hi> by combination with the reſt of the Members before named (in furher proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:187881:7"/>
of the deſignes mentioned in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> late preſident of <hi>Ireland</hi> was both faithfull and vigilant while he was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the fame Kingdome, and bad now this laſt ſpring made proviſions ready to march into the field, and that the Lord Baron of <hi>Brohill</hi> Generall of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments horſe in <hi>Munſter,</hi> and Col. Sir <hi>Arthur Loftus</hi> perſons of honour and reputation and of great fortunes in the ſaid Kingdome, lately came purpoſely into this Kingdome to exhibite and did exhibite many articles of high treaſon againſt the Lord <hi>Inchequin</hi> for betraying the Parliaments Army to the enemy (as formerly he had done) yet by the great power and violent interpoſition of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> Maſter <hi>Hollis</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> by the practiſe and combination aforeſaid, the ſaid Articles have been obſtructed, and the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe not ſuffered to come to a hearing, and the ſaid Lord <hi>Liſle</hi> haſtily called out of Ireland, and the power and command of the Parliament forces in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome committed to the ſaid Lord of <hi>Inchequin</hi> to the loſſe of this Summers ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and the expence of much treaſure to make new preparations of warre: and whereas the ſaid Lord <hi>Liſle</hi> being ſo ſuddenly called from thence as aforeſaid did deſigne and depute Sir <hi>Hardres Waller</hi> Knight Major Generall of the forces there, a man of known integrity and courage both for his ſervice in <hi>England</hi> and in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and of conſiderable fortunes, there to take care of the ſaid Lord <hi>Liſles</hi> forces till the pleaſure of the Parliament might be further known. The ſaid Lord of <hi>Inchequin</hi> upon the receipt of a Letter from the ſaid Sir <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> Maſter <hi>Hollis,</hi> and Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton</hi> or one of them, or from ſome other perſon by their or one of their direction, privity, procurement did expreſſe that he had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or direction from <hi>London</hi> that no man that favoured the Independents (under which name the ſaid Lord of <hi>Inchequin</hi> hath comprehended all men that have ſhewed themſelves oppoſite to tyranny and arbitrary government) ſhould have any truſt or warrant there, nay though they were of another judgement yet if they would not proſecute the Independents, they ſhould not be imployed there, or words to that effect; and under colour thereof the ſaid Sir <hi>Hardres Waller,</hi> and all others that formerly had had their Commiſſions from the ſaid L. <hi>Liſle</hi> while he commanded, were diſplaced; to the diſcouragement of thoſe other faithfull perſons, and to the Parl. and to the great diſſervice and danger of the loſſe of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. That whereas a Committee of the Houſe of Commons hath been late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appointed by the Parliament to conſider of Propoſitions for the ſettling and preſervation of <hi>Wales,</hi> whereof the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Glyn</hi> were and are Members, and to report the ſame to the Houſe; They the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis</hi> and Maſter <hi>Glyn,</hi> with others of the ſaid Committee, did on the 30. day of <hi>April</hi> now laſt paſt, without any authority of Parliament before any report made to the Houſe of their own accord (in ſtead of ſettling and preſerving <hi>Wales</hi>) order that all Committees for Sequeſtrations ſhould forbeare all procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of Sequeſtration againſt all, or any of the Inhabitants of <hi>Wales;</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome few perſons were upon general heads excepted, Yet by vertue of that
<pb facs="tcp:187881:8"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> peace and Commiſſioners of Aſſociation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were as active in raiſing money, and preſſing men to ſerve againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament as any others, all the Commiſſioners of array, that did or ſhould at any time come in, and ſubmit to the Parliament or their Commanders in chiefe, without any limitation of time, all that had born Armes againſt the Parliament, unleſſe they were Governours and other Officers of war, that held out ſome Towne, Caſtle, or Fort againſt the Parliament; All diſaffected, and ſcandalous Miniſters (though in their Sermons they uſually reviled and ſcandalized the Parliament, and their proceedings calling them Rebels and Traitors, and not only incenſing the people aginſt the Parliament, but uſually taking up Arms, and leading their Pariſhioners in arms upon any alarum againſt the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, and many other deſperate Delinquents have been, and ſtill are taken off and freed from ſequeſtration, and the ſaid order was ſent to every Committee in <hi>Wales,</hi> in ſeverall Letters contrary to ſeverall Orders and Ordinances of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and contrary to the rules of Juſtice and equity, which ſhould imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally be adminiſtred as well in <hi>Wales</hi> as in other places of this Kingdome, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ill-affected Gentry and Miniſtry of that Country are growne ſo high and inſolent, that honeſt men dare ſcarce live amongſt them; ſo as that which was intended by the Parliament, to ſettle and preſerve <hi>Wales,</hi> is (by the practice of the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Glyn</hi>) perverted to the danger and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of it.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. That the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Glyn,</hi> have further ingratiated themſelves with the Delinquents of <hi>Wales,</hi> and prepared them for their ſaid Deſignes in manner following, <hi>viz.</hi> he the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis</hi> hath within two yeares laſt paſt, counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced and protected many of the moſt notorious and dangerous De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent within the ſeverall Counties of South-<hi>Wales,</hi> namely the Lord of <hi>Carberry,</hi> and others in <hi>Carnarvon</hi>-ſhire, Maſter <hi>Carue</hi> and others in <hi>Glamo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gan</hi>-ſhire, Maſter <hi>Morgan,</hi> late Knight of the ſhire, Maſter <hi>Iohn Herbert</hi> and others in <hi>Brecnock</hi>-ſhire, Maſter <hi>Gwyn,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Lewis,</hi> and divers others in <hi>Radnor</hi>-ſhire, by freeing ſome of them altogether from compoſitions, though Sequeſtred; by labouring di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Members of the Houſe and of Committees to be favourable in compounding with others, and to admit of ſuch to their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions as were uncapable thereof; And the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis</hi> hath animated, and encouraged ſome of the ſaid perſons to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue their fidelity to the Kings cauſe, promiſing them, that if they would ingage their friends with the King for him, he &amp; his would be their friends in the Parliament, inſomuch as his friends (the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents in thoſe parts) have lately looked upon him as a riſing man
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:187881:8"/>
when the King ſhall come to <hi>London,</hi> which hath lately been their conſtant boaſting. And the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis</hi> hath within two yeares laſt paſt, cauſed divers that had been Commiſſioners for the King, and had preſſed men, and raiſed money to promote the late warre againſt the Parliament, namely his brother Maſter <hi>Thomas Lewis,</hi> Maſter <hi>Gwyn,</hi> Maſter <hi>Charles Walbiffe,</hi> Maſter <hi>Meredith Lewis</hi> Maſter <hi>Edward Williams,</hi> and many others, to be Commiſſioners of the Peace, and Committee men for the ſaid County of <hi>Brecknock;</hi> inſomuch as thoſe that have been moſt active and faithfull to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, have bin, and ſtill are outvoted in thoſe places, and can doe no conſiderable ſervice for the Parliament, and the rather for that the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis</hi> hath alſo procured one <hi>Edward Williams</hi> (his owne Kinſman, and one much diſaffeected to the Parliament) to be Sollicitor of Sequeſtrations in the ſaid County, who is &amp; hath been very remiſſe and corrupt therein. And the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis</hi> hath by the meanes aforeſaid lately procured Maſter <hi>Edmond Lewis</hi> his Sonne (though unfit for that imployment) to be choſen and returned Burges for <hi>Brecknock;</hi> which that he might the better effect he kept the writ for election of the ſaid Burges above eight months, in his own cuſtody before it was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the Sheriffe of the ſaid County. And likewiſe that the ſaid Mr. <hi>Iohn Glyn</hi> within two yeares laſt paſt hath procured ſeveral perſons that have lately beene Commiſſioners of Array and in Armes againſt the Parliament in <hi>Northwales</hi> viz. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers, to be named in the Commiſſions of the peace for the Countyes of <hi>Denbigh</hi> and <hi>Carnarvon,</hi> and other Counties there, and to be put in other great place; of truſt and command there. And amongſt others Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Glyn</hi> his brother, who was lately a Collonel in the Kings Army is by the ſaid Maſter <hi>John Glyns</hi> procurement become Governour of the Town and Caſtle of <hi>Carnarvon</hi> and Admirall or Viceadmirall of the Iriſh Seas, to the endangering of thoſe Counties lying upon the Coaſts towards <hi>Ireland</hi> and to the feare and diſcouragement of the well affected Inhabitants of thoſe places.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. That the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis,</hi> being heretofore (during theſe troubles) Governour of <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> a Garriſon for the Parliament, in which time he received much of the publike Treaſure, for which he hath not yet given an Accompt, did while he was Governour there frequently hold cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondencie and intelligence with the Kings Party about the delivery up of the ſaid Garriſon; inſomuch as although Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> and divers others in that Garriſon were proclaimed Trait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs to the King yet he by the Kings ſpeciall Command was ſpared, the King affirming That the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis</hi> was his Friend and that he was confident hee would doe him good ſervice, or to that effect. And although he then was a Parliament-man and Governour of <hi>Portſmouth</hi> as aforeſaid, and his eſtate in the ſaid County
<pb facs="tcp:187881:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:187881:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:187881:10"/>
of <hi>Brecknock,</hi> being of the value of above 600. pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> was three years in the Kings Quarters, yet the ſame was never Seqeuſtred: And ſince the Parliament hath prevailed, Collonel <hi>Herbert Price,</hi> Eſquire, having been Governour of <hi>Brecknoc</hi> for the King againſt the Parliament, being ſequeſtred, the ſaid Sir <hi>William Lewis</hi> by his ſollicitations to the Committee, procured the perſonall Eſtate of the ſaid Collonel <hi>Price,</hi> which the Committee of the County had found out, and cauſed to be brought to <hi>Morgan Aubrayes</hi> houſe in <hi>Brecknoc,</hi> to be reſtored unto him, without any ſatisfaction to the State, and hath procured his the ſaid Col. <hi>Price</hi>'s lands in the ſaid County of <hi>Brecknoc,</hi> being worth about 300 pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> to be let to a friend of the ſaid Col. <hi>Prices,</hi> to his wives uſe, at fifty pounds <hi>per Annum</hi> contrary to the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the ſeverall Ordinances of Parliament made in that behalfe.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. That the ſaid M. <hi>John Glyn,</hi> or ſome other perſon or perſons, by his direction, conſent, or privity, or to his uſe, hath (during his being a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Houſe of Commons, taken rewards of ſeverall perſons for ſervice done them in the Houſe, as namely amongſt others, divers Drovers from <hi>Wales,</hi> who by his means and procurement had an allowance by Order of the Houſe for three thouſand pounds, in ſatisfaction of loſſes they had ſuſtained by the Enemy, did pay unto the wife of the ſaid M. <hi>Glyn,</hi> the ſumme of an hundred pounds, as a reward for his ſaid ſervice.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. That the ſaid M. <hi>John Glyn,</hi> as he hath been moſt active to bring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Commiſſion of Peace, and into other places of Authority, divers noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Delinquents in North <hi>Wales,</hi> as aforeſaid, ſo hath been as active, as much as in him lies, to put out, and keep out of the <hi>Militia,</hi> and Common-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>London</hi> and out of the Commiſſion of Peace for <hi>Middleſex,</hi> many emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and faithfull men, that have laid out their eſtates, and adventured their lives for defence of the Parliament and City, in the time of their greateſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity; namely, Alderman <hi>Pennington,</hi> Collonel <hi>Tichborne,</hi> M. <hi>Eſtwick,</hi> Mr. <hi>Moyer,</hi> and others, contrary to the Declaration of both Kingdomes, which hath aſſured all lawfull favour and encouragement to thoſe that have beene faithfull, and ſhall ſo continue to the Parliament: which doings muſt needs tend to the giving a freſh occaſion and power to the Enemy againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments beſt friends, to the diſhonour of the Parliament, and the indanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. That the ſaid Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> M. <hi>Hollis,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Lewis,</hi> have by their power and countenance, as Members of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, both joyntly and ſeverally, uſed means to obſtruct the courſe of Juſtice, and have interpoſed themſelves in ſeverall Cauſes, and by word of mouth mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and perſwaded Judges and other Officers, on the behalfe of ſuch as they conceive to be their friends: Amongſt others, whereas a great Cauſe was lately depending in the Houſe of Lords, betweene Alderman <hi>Langham</hi> and Captain <hi>Lymery,</hi> and Counſell was met for the pleading thereof, the ſaid Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> M. <hi>Hollis,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Lewis,</hi> did repaire to the Earle of <hi>Rutland</hi> about the ſame; and the ſaid Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton</hi> told the ſaid Earle,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:187881:10"/>
that they (meaning himſelfe, and the ſaid M. <hi>Hollis,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Lewis</hi>) were fully ſatisfied concerning the Juſtice of <hi>Langhams</hi> Cauſe; and therfore as the ſaid Earle did reſpect them the ſaid Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> M. <hi>Hollis,</hi> and Sir <hi>VVilliam Lewis</hi> or expected from them, he the ſaid Earle of <hi>Rutland</hi> ſhould give his Vote for <hi>Langham;</hi> or uſed words to that effect; which alſo was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by the ſaid M. <hi>Hollis</hi> in words, and agrreed unto by the ſaid Sir <hi>VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Lewis,</hi> as appeared by his preſence and geſture. And the ſaid Sir <hi>VVilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Lewis</hi> did exerciſe the ſame power in a Cauſe of <hi>Iohn Gunters,</hi> or others.</p>
            <p n="21">XXI. That the ſaid M. <hi>Anthony Nichols</hi> although about foure yeares ſince he was by the Committee of Priviledges voted, that he was not a Member fit to ſit in the Houſe, by reaſon his election was void, yet he the ſaid M. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chols</hi> doth not only ſit and Vote there as a Member, but by his power and threats in the Weſt-Countries, and by his ſolicitations, and indirected pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, hath brought in or procured to bee brought in, about twenty eight Members more out of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> on purpoſe to carry on the deſignes and practiſes before mentioned, and to make a faction in the ſaid Houſe: and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the ſelfe-denying Ordinance, he the ſaid M. <hi>Nichols</hi> doth ſtill hold a place in the Tower formerly conferred upon him by the Houſe, and receiveth the profits thereof to his owne uſe.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. That the ſaid M. <hi>Nicholls,</hi> hath ſince his ſitting in the Houſe as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid taken rewards for ſervice done there, namely, whereas Sir <hi>William Vuedall</hi> Knight, for deſerting the Parliament and going to <hi>York</hi> with the King was ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended the Houſe, he the ſaid M. <hi>Nicholls</hi> for the ſumme of one hundred pounds or one hundred fifty pounds paid unto him, or to his uſe, by the ſaid Sir <hi>William Vuedall</hi> or ſome for him, did by miſ-informations to the Houſe procure the ſaid Sir William Vuedall to be re-admitted a Member of the ſaid Houſe, and the ſaid M. <hi>Nicholls</hi> while he was a Member of the Committee for ſafety, he and others of the ſaid Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittee having iſsued forth a warrant for ſearching <hi>Greenwich</hi>-houſe, he the ſaid M. <hi>Nicholls</hi> did under-hand acquaint one of the Queens officers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and thereby prevented the deſigne of the ſaid Committee, to the great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervice of the Parliament and Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="23">XXIII. That the ſaid M. <hi>Long</hi> at the beginning of the late warres not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving courage ſufficient to perform his duty in military affairs, did out of cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe or other unworthineſſe procure a command of a troop of horſe under his Excellency the L. Gen. the late E. of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> but when ever his ſaid troop came upon any ſervice, he the ſaid M. <hi>Long</hi> out of feare or treachery unworthily abſented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and never was ſeen or known to charge the enemy in perſon, though his troop often engaged, namely, at the battell at Edgehill, when he ſaw there was like to be blowes, he the ſaid M. <hi>Long</hi> left the field, and never charged before his Troop, and at the battell or fight at <hi>Brainford,</hi> though his Troop was there, yet he ſtaid at <hi>London</hi> till the danger was paſt, and fighting done; and when his Troop was ſent into the Weſt, he took no other notice of it but to receive his pay, and in the mean while he repaired into the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and procured a commiſſion to be a Collonell of Horſe, and in ſtead of fighting againſt the Parliaments ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies he betook himſelf to plunder, and oppreſſe the Parliaments friends there,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:187881:11"/>
&amp; contrary to order, and without any authority or exigencies of War, compelling him thereto, inforced great ſummes of money, &amp; many Horſes, and other proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the Country, namely from M. <hi>Tho. Manwood,</hi> a man well affected, who had the Generalls protection, (whoſe horſes were taken from his plough) and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to the great loſſes and oppreſſion of the people, and to the great diſhonor of the Parliament, whoſe ſervice he nevertheleſſe neglected, and hath not hitherto given an account of the great ſummes of money and other things he ſo exacted from the Country as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="24">XXIV. That the ſaid M. <hi>Long</hi> afterwards (upon pretence of ſome loſſes ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteined by the enemy, and ſome great ſervice he had done for the State) did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure of the Houſe a great office in the Coancery, namely to be the chief Regiſter of that Court, wherein his skill was little, and whereof he was and is ſtill alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uncapable; and although for a time upon the ſelf denying Ordinance, he was diſplaced; yet upon the motion, or by the power and means of the ſaid M. <hi>Hollis</hi> he hath obtained the ſame office, to the great prejudice of skilfull Clerks, that have been bred up in the ſame Court, and to the diſſervice of the Common-wealth, and the diſhonor of the Houſe.</p>
            <p n="25">XXV. That the ſaid M. <hi>Long</hi> on purpoſe to drive on the deſignes in the ſaid generall Charges expreſſed, hath for the ſpace of two yeares laſt paſt, uſually preſſed and urged ſeverall Members to give their Votes ſuch wayes as he pleaſed, and to that end and purpoſe doth conſtantly plac himſelf neare the doore of the Houſe, that when any debate is concerning any deſigne wherein his party is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, he the ſaid M. <hi>Long</hi> hath uſed much tampering and violence to ſuch of his own party as wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d go out of the Houſe, and hath perſwaded them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue there for their Votes, and he the ſaid M. <hi>Long</hi> in caſe any ſuch have gone out of the Houſe, hath been very inquiſitive where they may be found, that ſo he may go for them, when the buſineſſe in debate comes near to be put to the vote and when they come not according to his expectation doth ordinarily run out of the Houſe himſelf to call them, and drive them in again, that he hath beene commonly called (by thoſe that are without the Houſe, and have taken notice of his actions) the <hi>Parliament-driver,</hi> whereby the freedome of the Members is taken from them, the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of the Parliaments proceedings much ſcandalized and many times evill and dangerous deſignes drove on in a faction by Votes, to the great prejudice of the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>All which matters and things the ſaid Army ſhall and will be ready (in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient time) to make good by proof upon Oath, as his Honorable Houſe ſhall direct. And for that by reaſn of the ſtraightneſse of time, and other more weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Affairs of the Army, they could not ſo fully finiſh and accompliſh the ſaid Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles; therefore the ſaid Army do ſtill reſerve further liberty to adde other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles againſt the ſaid Members, or any of them, at any time before their Triall as occaſion ſſiall ſerve.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By the appointment of his Excellency</hi> Sir THOMAS FAIRFAX. <hi>and his Councell of Warre.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Signed <hi>John Ruſhworth</hi> Secretary.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb facs="tcp:187881:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187881:12"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187881:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
